Guide to the Ralph McCallister Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ralph McCallister papers
1951-1983
MS 1202
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The papers consist of correspondence and printed matter relating primarily to Ralph McCallister's service as director and vice-president of the Chautauqua Institution (1944-1961). Major correspondents in the papers are Rebecca Richmond who was active in promoting Chautauqua activities and Alburn E. Skinner, a trustee.
McCallister, Ralph, 1905-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ralph McCallister, 1980-1983.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Ralph McCallister (1905-) deal primarily with his association with the Chautauqua Institution, where he served as director of programs and education and as vice-president from 1944-1961. The correspondence, 1951-1961, is with both Chautauqua staff and summer visitors. There is a large section of letters to and from Rebecca Richmond, author of Invitation to Chautauqua. Mrs. Richmond was responsible for the creation of the Writers' Workshop and the Bell Tower scholarship at Chautauqua.
McCallister resigned his post in 1961, objecting to the manner in which the Chautauqua Institution was being administered. There is a great deal of correspondence concerning the events which led to his retirement and public reaction to his decision to leave Chautauqua.
Biographical / Historical
Ralph McCallister was born in Carmi, Illinois on September 28, 1905. He received his Ph.B. from the University of Chicago in 1930 and his M.A. from the University of Michigan in 1936. From 1936-1948 McCallister directed the Adult Education Council in Chicago. In 1944 he became the Director of Programs and Education, and Vice-President of the Chautauqua Institution, a position he held until 1961. Bewteen 1962 and 1970, McCallister coordinated many programs and projects in adult and higher education in the Carolinas and Virginia. In 1970 he became the Associate Director, Office of Medical Studies at the School of Medicine, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Adult education; Education; Educators; McCallister, Ralph, 1905-; Richmond, Rebecca, d. 1961; Skinner, Alburn Edward, 1872-1958; Chautauqua Institution
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1959 Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1959 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Between Rebecca Richmond and Ralph McCallister, 1951-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - And memorial tributes concerning the death of Rebecca Richmond, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Alburn E. Skinner, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Concerning the Writers' Workshop, Chautauqua Institute, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1961 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1961 Mar-Dec, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1962-1980, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Invitation to Chautauqua: financial and publicity material, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reference material concerning Chautauqua Institute, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Resume and employment information of Ralph McCallister, 1961-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Reprints, clippings, reviews, and other printed material, 1955-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)